Guide to the Jay Haley Collection, 1957-2007 M1733
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1957-2004
  - Subseries 1.3 Personal, 1957-2004
    - 1988 May - Aug. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Haley’s disagreement with Dr. Lee Combrick-Graham on drug-based treatment for schizophrenics; on the polarized ideology of schizophrenia treatment: Haley versus Anderson-Goldstein, see letter by Loren R. Mosher. Some of the correspondents include: Lee Combrick-Graham, Loren R. Mosher, and John H. Weakland.
    - 1988 Sept. - Dec. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Haley declines Albert R. Roberts’ invitation to write a chapter entitled “Family Abuse and Sexual Abuse Treatment: Issues, Stages, and the Therapeutic Process,” for a book on violence.
    - 1989 Jan. - June (Box 6, Folder 4)
      On the creation of Haley’s audio book, The First Therapy Session; “Family Experiments at the MRI: A Historical Note” for MRI’s 30th anniversary.
    - 1989 July - Dec. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Haley’s comment on Bill O’Hanlon’s book in progress, An Uncommon Casebook: The Complete Clinical Work of Milton Erickson, M. D.; transcript of Haley interview commemorating the 10th anniversary of The Milton H. Erickson Institute of San Diego; The Milton H. Erickson Foundation, Phoenix, planning the Evolution of Psychotherapy Conference; Haley’s parameters for judging a colleague’s paper, see letter to Carlos Sluzki. Some of the correspondents include: Bill O’Hanlon, Michael D. Yapko, Jeffrey K. Zeig, and Steve Andreas.
    - 1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Update on the Dec. Evolution of Psychotherapy Conference organized by The Milton H. Erickson Foundation; Haley’s letter to the “Ericksonian Foundation Newsletter” editor, Michael D. Yapko, disagreeing with the content of an interview with Albert Ellis; initial stages of the creation of the Milton H. Erickson documentary film with Madeleine Richeport; Moshe Talmon’s book on single-session therapy; as part of Haley’s feedback to Susan H. McDaniel’s paper (title not specified), he offers an explanation of what family systems therapy, or family therapy, is in his view; clarification on how the term “double bind” was coined, see letter to Douglas Flemons; “The One Way Screen – An Historical Note,” see letter to Cheryl White; transcription of Haley’s talk “Compulsory Therapy for Both Client and Therapist,”(with added corrections) for the American Association for Marriage and Family Therapy annual Conference in Washington DC, see letter by Kimberly A. Tilley. Some of the correspondents include: Jeffrey K. Zeig, Herb Lustig, Elizabeth Erickson, Moshe Talmon, Susan H. McDaniel, and Douglas Flemons.
    - 1991 Jan. - June (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Haley’s life-transforming impact on a colleague, see letter by Michael R. Fox; Douglas Flemons writes to Haley about his new book, Completing Distinctions and elaborates on some of his and Haley’s views in regard to therapy and Zen. Some of the correspondents include: Michael R. Fox and Douglas Flemons.
    - 1991 July - Dec. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Haley is invited to participate in the seminar, in Santiago Chile, Development in Family Therapy organized by the Milton H. Erickson Foundation, Inc. Some of the correspondents include: Jeffrey K. Zeig
    - 1992 Jan. - Apr. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Haley accepts to be named Editor Emeritus for the Family Process journal Some of the correspondents include: Peter Steinglass.
    - 1992 May - Dec. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Haley discusses his article “Paradoxes in Play, Fantasy and Psychotherapy,” from 1955 with Ewald Vervaet; Haley answers questions on the chapter, “He never had a chance,” (dealing with stuttering) from his book Ordeal Therapy, see letter by and to Susan Paskerian; reviews to Haley’s article “How to be a therapy supervisor without knowing how to change anyone,” see letter from Douglas H. Sprenkle, editor of Journal of Marital and Family Therapy; reviews to Haley’s article “Therapist Abuse,” see letter from Peter Steinglass, editor of Family Process journal; Haley offers his view on family therapy and systemic thinking, see letter to Salvador Minuchin. Some of the correspondents include: Douglas H. Sprenkle, Peter Steinglass and Salvador Minuchin.
    - 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      On publishing Haley’s chapter “Zen and the Art of Therapy” from his book Jay Haley on Milton H. Erickson in The Family Therapy Networker, see letters by Richard Simon.
    - 1994 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Reception of Haley’s article “Zen and the Art of Therapy” published in The Family Therapy Networker, see letters by Tamara Engel and Mark Rivett; Haley recounts Gregory Bateson’s work as an ethnologist starting in the 1940s serving a variety of ethnic groups at the Menlo Park Veterans Hospital, see letter to Mony Elkaīm.
    - 1995 - 1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      On schizophrenia and the systems thinking, see letter by Michael E. Kerr; Haley’s dilemma on accepting an invitation to participate in the 1997 Twenty Fifth Year Celebration of the Family Therapy Conference in Chicago, see letter to Betty Mac Kune-Karrer; on using laughter/humor to give a new meaning for an old experience; the command function of language and hypnosis; people as functioning systems; problems with classification, see letters from and to Steve Andreas; Haley pokes fun at some of the professional literature’s turgid nature, see letter to Brian Cade; Loren Mosher’s letter of resignation from the American Psychiatric Association; tribute to Jay Haley by Lyman Wynne. Some of the correspondents include: Michael E. Kerr, Betty Mac Kune-Karrer, Steve Andreas, Brian Cade, Loren Mosher, and Lyman Wynne.
    - 2000 - 2004, Short, Dan (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Effects of Haley’s Strategies of Psychotherapy on a young draftee doing assessment and counseling work at the Mental Hygiene Consultation Service in Ft. Gordon, Georgia, see letter by Jay Lappin; Haley’s feedback on David Grove’s manuscript Invisible Men; Haley accepts the invitation to join the American Psychotherapy Seminar Center, see letters by and to Alfred D. Yassky Some of the correspondents include: Dan N. Short, Jay Lappin, David Grove, Alfred D. Yassky
    - Personal: Potential Speaking Engagements I, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      A large proportion of the correspondence consists of invitations for professional speaking. Haley filed the1972-73 invitations separately, but all others were filed chronologically with the personal correspondence.
    - Personal: Potential Speaking Engagements II, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Misc. Letters. Restricted (Box 33, Folder 3)
- Series 2. Haley's Writings, 1958-2003
  Scope and Contents
  Haley’s writings are organized by subject and within each subject by date. The first two subseries are the largest and also the most important, in particular his writings on teaching psychotherapy.
  - Subseries 2.1 Psychotherapy as a Profession, 1958-2003
    - "The Art of Psychoanalysis" (reprints), 1958 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "Control in Psychoanalytic Psychotherapy" (reprint), 1959 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - "Transference Revisited" by Jay Haley and Donald D. Jackson (reprint); Strategies of Psychotherapy (typescript), 1963 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "The Amiable Hippie" (journal), 1968 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "The Art of Being a Failure as a Therapist" (journals), 1969; 1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - "How to Criticize Your Fellow Therapists" (journal), 1970 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Problem Solving Therapy - Funny Coincidence Department (typescript and letters), 1976-1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - A Quiz for Young Therapists (reprint); Social Control Versus Therapy (typescript), 1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "Changes in Therapy" (four typescripts and one galley proof), 1977 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Reflections (on the trends in the fields of therapy, typescript), 1979 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - "Therapy - A New Phenomenon" (photocopies of printed article), 1987 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - The Businessman's Guide to Therapy; The Therapy Industry (typescripts), 1989-2000 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Why Not Long Term Therapy? (typescript and letters), 1990 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Zen and the Art of Therapy and Other Essays (Chapters 1- 6, typescripts), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Zen and the Art of Therapy and Other Essays (Chapters 7- 12, typescripts), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Learning Theory and Family Therapy (typescript), circa 1996 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Changing Times in Therapy (rough drafts, typescripts), 1997 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - How to Be an Abusive Therapist (typescript), circa 2000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "A Response to Donald Meichenbaum" for the Evolution of Psychotherapy: A Meeting of the Minds (galley proof and letter), 2003 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "What Therapists Have in Common" (typescript and galley proof), 2003 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Ethics in Therapy (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Impossible Situations and Unreasonable Solutions by Jay Haley and Neil Schiff (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Does Therapy Require Educating Clients? (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - In Defense of Psychoanalysis (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Toward a More Sensible Therapy (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Mandatory Therapy Meeting (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Traditional Therapy vs Compulsory Therapy (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Psychotherapy miscellaneous: directives, strategies, ethics, codes, and a questionnaire (typsescripts) (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - No Orthodox Procedures (on marriage therapy, typed note-cards) (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous Fragments (typescripts) (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 2.2 Teaching Psychotherpay, 1965-2006
    - Diagnosis from Two Points of View, (typescript), 1959 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Marcha's Notes on Haley's Training: Therapy with Disturbed Young People; Paradox, (copies of handwritten notes); Dick Stuart, Behavior Modification with Couples, (copies of handwritten notes), 1976 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Communication in Learning and Psychotherapy (typescripts, 4 drafts, and letters), 1965 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - How to Supervise Therapy without Knowing How (typescript), 1993 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Development of a Theory: The Rise and Demise of a Research Project, (typescript) (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - "How to Be a Therapy Supervisor without Knowing How to Change Anyone" (reprint), 1993 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "How to Teach Psychotherapy" (reprint), 1994 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Learning and Teaching Therapy (letters, new title announcement, book covers, reviews), 1994-1996 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Learning and Teaching Therapy ((typescript of early draft with different title, Strategies of Therapy Supervision), 1996 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Learning and Teaching Therapy (editor's comments and annotated typescript). Chapter 1 - 6, 1995 (January) (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Learning and Teaching Therapy (editor's comments and annotated typescript). Chapter 7 - 11, 1995 (January) (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Learning and Teaching Therapy (publisher's edited typescript) Chapter 1 - 6, 1995 (October) (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Learning and Teaching Therapy (publisher's edited typescript and letter) Chapter 7 - 11, 1995 (October) (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Teaching Therapy, (annotated typescript) (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Changes in Therapy (typescript), 1997 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Computer Monitor Supervision (4 typescripts), 1998 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Therapy Supervision (typescript) (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - What to Know; How to Do (typescripts) (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Changes in Therapy in a Different Way (typed note-cards for talk) (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Syllabus for US International University; Workshop: Directive Family Therapy (typscripts), 2001 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Approaches to Psychotherapy (fragment, notes for lecture, typescript) (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Family and Individual Therapy: Similarities, (annotated typescript) (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 2.2.5 Strategic (Directive) Therapy, 1971-2007; In later years Haley preferred the term directive therapy over strategic therapy
    - Strategic Therapy When a Child is Presented as the Problem, (typescripts of paper and related correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - The Art of Strategic Therapy, with Madeleine Richeport-Haley. Part I, (edited typescript), 2003 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - The Art of Strategic Therapy, with Madeleine Richeport-Haley. Part II, (edited typescript), 2003 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - The Art of Strategic Therapy (dust jacket); How to Do Strategic Therapy, table of contents, (earlier version of book), 2003 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - The Strategy of Psychotherapy (typescript) (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Directive Therapy; Strategies and Techniques Used in Therapy, Questionnaire; Appendix: Therapist Manual for Family Treatment of Obsessive Compulsives; Psychotherapy for Smarties (typescripts), 2006 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Directive Family Therapy, with Madeleine Richeport-Haley. Part I, (galley proofs with annotations), 2007 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Directive Family Therapy, with Madeleine Richeport-Haley. Part II, (galley proofs with annotations), 2007 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2.3 Milton H. Erickson MD, 1957-1993
    - Explorer of Hypnosis (typescript), 1957 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - On the Transcripts of Conversations with Erickson (correspondence), 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson (typescripts of drafts, notes, and fragments), 1973 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson (typescript of draft, Part I), 1973 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson (typescript of draft, Part II), 1973 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson (typescripts of draft with annotations, and notes), 1973 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - The Contribution to Therapy (typescript), 1982 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Epilogue for the new edition of Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson (typescript), 1985 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - "Remembering Erickson: A Dialogue Between Jay Haley and John Weakland" (photocopies of book with annotations), 1985; Exists also as film (1997), see Series 7 Media, box 55. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "Zen and the Art of Therapy" (typescript), 1992 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      General note
      Haley believed that Zen was the only way to explain Erickson's directive therapy.
    - Commentary on the Writings of Milton H. Erickson, M.D. from the book Jay Haley on Milton H. Erickson (typescript and photocopies of printed book), 1993 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence on Jay Haley on Milton H. Erickson(typed letters), 1993 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - "The Therapy of Milton H. Erickson." Topical Panel. The Evolution of Psychotherapy Conference (typescript) (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Treatment of an Acute Hysterical Depression (annotated typescript); On Erickson's Approach to Sex Therapy, (audio transcript); Similaritites Between Psychotic Behavior and Manifestations of Hypnotic Trance. Haley and John Weakland in conversation with Erickson (audio transcript) (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Erickson's Stories; Cases Condensed (typescripts) (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2.4 Hypnosis, 1958-1999
    - "An Interactional Explanation of Hypnosis" (reprint), 1958 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - "A Transcript of a Trance Induction with Commentary" by Erickson. M., Haley, J. and Weakland, J. (journal), 1959 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Hypnotic Seminar (typescript of lecture), 1999 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 2.5 Gregory Bateson; The Bateson Project; Paradoxes, 1953-1993
    - Guidelines on Paradoxes; Misc. Notes (typescripts and mss.), circa 1953 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Development of a Theory: A History of a Research Project. Part I (annotated typescript), 1953-1963 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Development of a Theory: A History of a Research Project. Part II (annotated typescript), 1953-1963 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Paradoxes in Play, Fantasy, and Psychotherapy (annotated typescript), 1955 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Paradojas en Juego, la Fantasía y la Psicoterapia (annotated typescript), 1955 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - "A Note on the Double Bind" by Bateson, G., Jackson, D., Haley, J., and Weakland, J. (photocopy of book), 1962 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Paradox in Therapy (with case example: Only on Sunday, typescripts), 1974 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - A Matter of Character by the Ghost of Gregory Bateson, with Madeleine Richeport-Haley (typescripts of drafts and related correspondence), 1993 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - The Great Tradition. On Gregory Bateson (typescript) (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2.6 Marriage and Family Therapy, 1962-2010
    - Classification of Communication Patterns in Families with Experimental Methods. Application for Research Grant, (typescripts), 1961 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - "Whither Family Therapy?" (annotated typescript and reprints), 1962 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - An Approach to the Problem of Classifying Families. Progress Report, (typescript), 1962 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Family Experiments: A New Type of Experimentation, (reprint); Experimental Program. Preliminary Set of Experiments: A) Cooperative Endeavors B) Competitive Endeavors, (typescript), 1962 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - "Marriage Therapy" (correspondence and reprint), 1963 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "Family Therapy and Research." Proposed Collection of Family Papers for Science and Behavior Books, (typescripts), circa 1964 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - "Research on Family Patterns: An Instrument Measurement," (photocopies), 1964 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Normal and Abnormal Families Tested in a Restricted Communication Setting. Essay and correspondence, (annotated typescript); Speech Sequences of Normal and Abnormal Families with Two Children, (typescript); Communication Problems in Marital Discord, (reprint), 1966-1967 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - "Experiment with Abnormal Families"; "Control in Brief Psychotherapy"; "Speech Sequences of Normal and Abnormal Families with Two Children Present" (reprint and photocopies), 1967 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - A Family Process Reader (old version, typescripts of references and letters), 1968 - 1970 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      Correspondence with Publisher Grune & Stratton, Inc. and Family Process Journal. Haley failed to obtain permission from Family Process to republish his articles. Some of the correspondents include: Duncan Mackintosh; John E. Bell; Nathan W. Ackerman; John H. Weakland; Lyman C. Wynne, and Milton H. Erickson.
    - Materials for Changing Families: A Family Therapy Reader. An Annotated Bibliography, (typescripts of reference lists, abstracts, contract, and letters), 1950 - 1970 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      Some of the corrspendents include: Ira D. Glick; Jason Aronson; Duncan Mackintosh
    - Institute for Training Family Therapy, Pennsylvania. Grant Proposal, (typescript), 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Reprints of Haley's Writings in the 1970s, 1971 - 1979 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Publications Included
      Family Therapy and Research, 1971; "Communication and Therapy: Blocking Metaphors," 1971; "Critical Overview of Present Status of Family Interaction Research," 1972; "Strategic Therapy When a Child is Presented as the Problem," 1973;"Why a Mental Health Clinic Should Avoid Family Therapy," 1975; "Family Therapy," 1975; "Dimensions of Family Therapy," with Cloe Madanes, 1977; "Ideas that Handicap Therapy with Young People," 1979.
    - Family Therapy with Disturbed Adolescents. Talk for the Institute of Marriage and Family Meeting in Zürich, (typescript), 1975 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Family Therapy of Delinquency, (typescripts and letters), 1979 - 1981 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Reprints of Haley's Wrintgs in the 1980s, 1980 - 1988 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      "How to be a Marriage Therapist Without Knowing Practically Anything," 1980; "On the Right to Choose One's Own Grandchildren," 1981; "Strategic Therapy and The Stages of Family Life," 1988
    - Haley's foreword to Practicing Family Therapy in Diverse Settings, by Michael Berger, Gregory J. Jurkovic and associates, (typescript), 1983 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - "Marriage or Family Therapy," (reprint and annotated typescript); Therapy Supervision; Toward a More Sensible Therapy, (typescripts), 1984 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Ordeal Therapy (photocopy of chapter VI, typescript of XII); Unpublished Cases. Not used in Ordeal Therapy, (typescripts), 1984 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - The Dual Hierarchy and Power in Marriage, (typescript); The Dual Hierarchy and the Problem of Children,(typescript); "Marriage and its Consequences," from Uncommon Therapy,(typescript of chapter), 1993 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence on Leaving Home: The Therapy of Disturbed Young People; Problem Solving Therapy: New Strategies for Effective Family Therapy, 1994 (Box 18, Folders 1)
    - Brave Men Run in My Family, (annotated typescript for talk), 1996 (Box 18, Folders 2)
    - "The Family Structure and its Importance to the Individual," (journal issue), 1996 (Box 18, Folders 3)
    - Leaving Home, (galley proofs) Part I, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Leaving Home, (galley proofs) Part II, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Unbalancing a Couple, (annotated typescript for talk), circa 2005 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Essays for Jay Haley Revisited, 2010 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Case Book, Part I, (annotated typescripts) (Box 19, Folder 3)
      List of cases
      Only on Sunday; Family Therapy without Parent Education; Handwashing; case with no title: divorcing couple with a son and daughter
    - Case Book, Part II, (annotated typescripts) (Box 20, Folder 1)
      List of Cases
      A Depressed Boy; Family Therapy Zen Family; Psychotic Youth; Anxious Woman with Sweating Hands; ms. fragments
    - Family Therapy Without Parent Education; The Affair (annotated typescripts) (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Critical Overview of Present Status of Family Interaction Research, (annotated typescript) (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Marriage Therapy. Clinical Demonstration, (various versions of talk, typescripts) (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Misc. Family Therapy Directives, (typescritps) (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Separated Materials note
      The First Interview in Family Therapy: A Primer; Supervision Notes; Rules of Relationships; Thérapie Familiale; Pharmacology vs Family Therapy; Possible Experiment, a child is doing badly in school in comparison with other children; ms. fragments
    - Delinquent Family Script. Bringing out Addiction. Therapist: Paul Riley, (typescript) (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (typescripts) (Box 21, Folders 3)
      Titles of undated typescripts
      The Art of Family Therapy; Social Context of Children; Child Therapy without Education; The Human Dilemma and Therapeutic Change; and The Conceptual Design of Minimal Strategies for Family Therapy
  - Subseries 2.7 Schizophrenia, 1950-2007
    - Early Drafts: A Hypothesis Regarding the Origin and Nature of Schizophrenia; The Family of the Schizophrenic: A Model System; An Invesitgation of the Characteristics of Schizophrenic Communication; Towards a Scientific Method in Psychiatry; and fragments, (typescripts and letters), 1956-1960 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Reprints: "Toward a Theory of Schizophrenia"; "The Family of the Schizophrenic: A Model System"; "An Interactional Description of Schizophrenia", 1956-1959 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - The Family of the Schizophrenic: A Descriptive Model, (typescripts of two versions), 1959 (Box 21, Folder 6)